Guide to the Clarence Urmy Papers, 1878-1936 M0020
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Clarence Urmy Papers,
1878-1936
M0020
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
1.0 Linear feet
Urmy, Clarence, 1858-1923
Biographical Note
Urmy, Clarence 1858-1923
He was born in San Francisco on July 10, 1858. He was the grandsoneof Elea Thomas who was one of the founders of the Methodist church in the state of California. Urmy's father was a methodist minister for 50 years. Urmy attended San Francisco public schools and then Napa College where he studied music and received a batchelor's degree. He worked for a number of years in music houses (Sherman and Clay in San Francisco). He continued to study voice at this time and did some performing in San Francisco and San Jose. He was the organist at Santa Clara Methodist Church and later at Trinity Episcopal Church in San Jose. He taught piano at the College of the Pacific and four years at San Jose Teachers' College.
Urmy was the first native poet of California. He published three volumes of collected verse: A Rosary of Rhyme, Vintage of Verse, and California Troubadour. Two more volumes were nearly ready for publication at his death: Wild Willow and Under the Toyon Tree. His poems appeared in a large number of national magazines. He also did dramatic and music criticism for the San Jose Mercury Herald.
Urmy died on June 3, 1923 in San Jose. A Clarence Urmy Memorial was established at Stanford in 1930, which consists of a prize given each year to the student submitting the best original poem.
Scope and Content Note
Urmy, Clarence
Correspondence to Urmy from publishers concerning his poetry. 1897-1922 ca. 35 items
Corresponding primarily to Mabel Urmy Seares from many sources largely concerning Clarence's works and various memorials set up in his honor. A number of these are from Alfred Lindsay and Helen Millar Lehman. ca. 60 items
Holograph and typescript of his poems and collected volumes ca. 100 items
Clippings of his works in print, both poetry and prose, criticism of music and drams by Urmy, and a number of clippings about him (including programs etc.) ca. 260 items.
Five photographs of Urmy
A scrapbook of autographs
A biography of Urmy by Mabel Urmy Seares
Ina Coolbrith--letters, poems, and clippings ca. 7 items
Inclusive dates: 1878-1936
Provenance
Gift of Urmy family, 1945.
Access Restrictions
None.
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Urmy from editors and publishers, 1897-1922
    - 1. William Doxey to Urmy, 1897, Jan. 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2. C” [Urmy] to “Mabel” [Mrs. Seares], 1897, Jan. 17 “
    - 3. C” [Urmy] to “Mabel” [Mrs. Seares] enclosed agreement between W.Doxey (publisher) and Urmy
    - 4. Horace Annesley Vachell, 1899, Nov. 29
    - 5. Robert Coningsley Clarke to “Dear Sir” [Urmy], 1900, May 8
    - 6. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy enclosed list of poems, 1905, Oct. 20
    - 7. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1905, Nov. 8
    - 8. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1905, Dec 4
    - 9. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1905, Dec. 9
    - 10. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1905, Dec. 18
    - 11. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1906, Feb. 10
    - 12. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1906, May 16
    - 13. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1906, May 16
    - 14. Marian Phelps to Urmy, 1906, Mar. 24
    - 15. Alfred Lindsay to Urmy, 1906, May 30; (copy)
    - 16. Alfred Holman to Urmy, 1907, Jan. 21
    - 17. Sheperd Knapp to Urmy, 1908, July 16
    - 18. to Mrs. F Seares, 1909, Apr. 22?; (postcard)
    - 19. A.M. Robertson to Urmy, 1912, May 10
    - 20. C.Alexander to Urmy, 1916, Apr. 2
    - 21. Marguerita Wilkenson to Urmy, 1917, Apr. 28
    - 22. Marguerita Wilkenson to Urmy, 1917, May 10
    - 23. Urmy to M. Wilkenson, [1917, May 12]
    - 24. M. Wilkenson to Urmy, 1917, May 17
    - 25. Will B. Turney to Mabel Seares, 1923, Jun. 24
    - 26. C.M. Dennis to Mabel Urmy Seares, 1923, Jun. 27
    - 27. Claud H. Simson to?, 1924, Jun. 24
    - 28. A.W. Noel Porter to Mabel Urmy Seares, 1924, Sept. 25
    - 29. Delancy Lewis to Mabel Urmy Seares, 1925, Sept 22
    - 30. Edward O'Day to Percival Urmy, 1926, Aug. 31
    - 31. F.P. Brown to Newton Barry enclosed letter to H.Roy Kelley to Mrs. Seares, 1926, Sept 20
    - 32. [J.Milshen] to H.Roy Kelley, 1927, Dec. 23
    - 33. [J.Milshen] to H.Roy Kelley, 1928, Jan. 16
    - 34. Garton D. Keyston to Percival Urmy, 1928, Oct. 4
    - 35. Sonnet in Memory of Clarence Urmy” by Francis Wm. Reid, 1930, Jan. 6 “; (photostat)
    - letter on the back to Mrs. M.U. Seares, 1930, Jan. 18
    - 36. Francis Wm. Reid to Mrs. Mabel Seares, 1930, Jan. 23
    - 37. Francis Wm. Reid to Mrs. Mabel Seares, 1930, Jan. 27
    - 38. Garton D. Keyston to Mabel Seares, 1930, Mar. 8
    - 39. Garton D. Keyston to Mabel Seares, 1930, Jun. 10
    - 40. Francis W. Reid to “friend” [Mabel Seares], 1930, Nov. 24
    - 41. Ina L. Cook to Mabel Seares, 1931, Jan. 9
    - 42. Ina L. Cook to Mrs. John R. Jarboe Kathryn Jarboe Bull, J.C.Bull, Esq., 1931, Jan. 18
    - 43. Francis W. Reid to Mrs. Mabel Seares, 1931, Apr. 2
    - 44. Garton D. Keyston to Mabel Seares, 1931, Jun. 4
    - 45. Garton D. Keyston to Mabel Seares, 1932, Jun. 6
      Scope and Contents note
      enclosed: 1st, 2nd, and 3rd place poems 1931-32
    - 46. Mrs. Frederick Seares to Mr. Reid, 1933, Jan. 27; (copy)
    - 47. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares, 1933, Jan. 23
    - 48. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares, 1933, Jan. 28
    - 49. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares, 1933, Jan. 30
    - 50. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares
    - 51. Francis W. Reid to Mabel Seares postcard with poem “Clarence Urmy”, 1933, Feb. 5
    - 52. Helen Tobin to Mabel Seares, 1933, Mar. 20; (postcd.)
    - 53. Mrs. Frederick Seares to Mrs. Lehman, 1933, Mar. 28; (copy)
    - 54. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares, 1933, Apr. 19; Postcard
    - 55. Helen Miller Lehman to Mabel Seares, 1933, May 8; postcard
    - 56. Garton D. Keyston to Mrs. Seares, 1936, Jun. 24
      enclosed: 1st, place poem; and “To Clarence Urmy”
    - 57. CTU” [Urmy] to Mr. Holman, ? Jan 14 “
    - 58. C” [Urmy] to “Mabel” [Mrs. Seares]
    - 59. [? B. Kulen] to Mrs. Seares, ? Dec. 7
- Manuscripts
  - Vol. 1 Apr. holograph notebook, 1878-Oct. 1880 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vol. 2 Nov. holograph notebook, 1880-Dec. 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vol. 3 Feb. holograph notebook, 1896-May 1901 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vol. 4 Jul. holograph notebook, 1901-Jan 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vol. 5 holograph notebook, 1904-4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vol. 6 holograph notebook, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vol 7 holograph notebook, 1910-13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wild Willow book of verse original manuscript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Under the Toyon Tree book of verse original manuscript (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - assorted manuscript verse -, dated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - assorted manuscript verse - (and some lists of his poems in the back), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - assorted prose (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Clippings
  - printed verse (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - “Peace” - prize winning poem in the San Francisco Chronicle contest (and letters praising it, and one from M.H. deYoung) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - printed prose (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - music and drama criticism (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - biographical (including diploma from Napa College and exerps from a diary, programs from muscial performance (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - concerning California (about Bret Hart, R.H. Stoddard and Clinton Scollard) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - photographs, (five of him) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Biography of Urmy by Mabel Urmy Seares (prepared about 1935-6, but she couldn't revise it because of illness) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook of autographs (and list of contents prepared by Urmy's brother Percival Urmy) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes: Aldrich, Thomas Bailey; Butterworth, Hezekiah Bryant, William Cullen; Coolbrith, Ina; Dorr, Julia; Davis, Jefferson; Fawcett, George D.; Hay, John; Holmes, Oliver Wendell; Howe, Julia Ward; Hubbard, Elbert; Jewett, Sarah O.; Kimball, Harriet; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth; Mason, Caroline Atwater; Moulton, Louise Chandler; Piatt, John James; Rexford, Eben Eugene; Sangster, Margaret Elizabeth; Thorpe, Rose Hartwick; Whitney, Adeline Dutton Train; Whittier, John Greenleaf; Wilde, Oscar; Winter, William
  - Ina Coolbrith letters, poems etc. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1. letters to Urmy, (9)
    - 2. poems, manuscript, (2)
    - 3. poem by Urmy
    - 4. clippings
    - 5. “Ina Coolbrith and Clarence Urmy” by Mabel Seares
    - 6. “Ina Coolbrith” Laura Bell Everett